[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is a question on detachment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can't the much-emphasized teaching of detachment in Buddhism, from sensory pleasures, sensuality, shall we say, diminish one's capacity to engage fully with life?
[SPEAKER_01]: If one ceases to find value in sensory... in sense experiences, couldn't this not lead to a lack of motivation or emotional... or lack of emotional richness and simply depression?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't have any passion anymore, well, then you got what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Depression?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, not quite.
[SPEAKER_00]: The depression is the lack of motivation, but not the lack of passion.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're trying to, very passionately, resist the mental state of depression that you find unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not, you're not unmoved by a depressed mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're very actively averse towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're very passionate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the depressed person is very passionate.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is still passionate.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's why depression hurts.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they were not passionate, well,
[SPEAKER_00]: Depression wouldn't hurt, which means they wouldn't be depressed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, lack of motivation is one thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lack of passion is another thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's lack of motivation when you've succeeded.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: There can be all sorts of reasons why you lack motivation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oversaturation can be one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Depression, choosing the path of less resistance, it then leads to the depression and, like, inability to make, to engage with any effort, becomes, like, monumental task, even the small efforts become unbearable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's all just through choosing passionately path of less resistance, for whatever reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe you were justified, maybe you were not.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that course of action takes in that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, yes, you could lose motivation, because you're truly dispassionate, and you would have fully understood cessation and the benefits of detachment and freedom that comes from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you were nowhere near passionate, and nowhere near depressed, and certainly nowhere near choosing the path of less resistance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're not going to get to a state of dispassion taught in Buddhism if you keep choosing the path of less resistance internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going against the stream.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's always choosing the path of higher resistance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever your mind doesn't want to do, that's what you need to look into.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Start justifying, rationalizing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, hold on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's... that's how you train the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you develop that whole Noble Eightfold Path and all the aspects that the Buddha talked about that then do result in factual dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even... even, say, in your ordinary life, you are dispassionate towards some things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not passionate towards everything all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just you don't recognize the value of that dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still measure everything through the lens of passion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, then, the issue of depression and so on, because the passion is there, but there is no more effort or zeal to fulfill it, to provide for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, it's just the unfulfilled pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, for the ordinary person, that idea of being detached and not emotionally charged is just...
[SPEAKER_00]: That's scary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that... yeah, that's a... that's a probably accurate observation, because, yeah, it wouldn't be the life the way you know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's... again, that's why people... nobody will accidentally commit to this, or on account of truly, correctly commit to this practice, because it leads you against pretty much all your familiarity.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's not pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only those who recognize the problem with life,
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem with passion, the problem with desires, the deep problem that really... it's not optional whether you should solve it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, those people could muster enough determination and inspiration to keep swimming against the stream.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would understand that the greatest pleasure and release from burden and freedom comes from the true detachment.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see, that attachment needs to be cultivated on the level of your lifestyle and all those choices that we talk about of renunciation and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not just like a mental exercise that having willingly engaged with acts, desires, cravings, intentions that lead to more attachment, that revolve around existing attachment, having not been keeping those choices in check,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, just on top of it, practice detachment in regard to things that you are still very much connected to.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just wishful thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just fantasy world.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's people, basically, that don't go against the stream, believe that they're practicing against the stream just to kind of appease the guilt of still flowing with the stream.